What the hell!
搞什么鬼?
Just let us do it tomorrow! Not today!
我们明天再做吧 不要今天做
Hey, I'm just the messenger.
我只是来传话的
Anyway, the mistress insisted that it be done today.
总之 女主人坚持一定要在今天做好
That old hag.
那个老妖婆
All the other times, she leaves us
她平常一向
in charge of guard duty.
不太干涉我们的工作
Maybe it has something to do with the reward of three horses.
或许是因为 有三匹马做为奖赏的关系吧
She wants a part of the reward?
她也想要分一杯羹?
What a greedy old hag.
还真是个贪心的老妖婆
Snake,
蛇
will you
可以让我
let me see my husband, Gardar?
看看我丈夫哥达吗?
No.
不行
He's injured, isn't he?
他受伤了 不是吗?
How...
他的...
How are his wounds?
他的伤势还好吗?
How would I know?
我怎么会知道?
Why do I have to care for an enemy who killed my subordinate?
我干嘛要在乎一个 杀了我手下的人的伤势?
Boss, here's a horse.
老大 马牵来了
All right. We'll be at the mistress' place.
好的 我们会待在女主人家
You go and take Arnheid back to Gramps' house.
你带阿奴纳回去老头子他家
They took the horses so we don't have any left.
他们把马都骑走了 这里一匹马都不剩
Are you serious? I have to walk...
真的假的?要我用走的...
her back?
送她回去?
Please, let me see my husband.
求求你 让我见我丈夫一面
I swear I'm not thinking of helping him escape.
我发誓我没有协助他逃走的意图
I just want to care for his wounds.
我只想照料他的伤口
Huh? Well...
什么?这个嘛...
But the boss said...
但老大说...
Hey!
喂 你们看
What's going on?
这是什么情况?
She's the cutie from Master Ketil's place.
他是凯特尔主人家的那个美女
Uh, the boss...
呃 老大...
The boss gave her permission
老大允许她
to care for Gardar's wounds. I'm not lying!
来照料哥达的伤口 我说的是真的
Gardar...
哥达
Arnheid!
阿奴纳
You were beaten?
你被打了?
Please cut this rope, Arnheid.
请把这条绳子砍断 阿奴纳
Let's go home.
我们回家吧
- Hey... - It's fine.
-喂... -不要紧
She doesn't have any tools that can cut the rope.
她身上没有任何能砍断绳子的工具
If you say so.
好吧 你说了算
Hey, Arnheid!
喂 阿奴纳
Your husband came all the way here to take you back.
你丈夫大老远跑来这里想带你回家
Forget about his wounds. Why don't you give him something more special?
别管他的伤势了 你不如给他一些更特别的服务算了
I can't care for his wounds if he's tied up like this.
他被这样绑着 我没办法处理他的伤口
Can you untie him just for now?
可以请你帮他松开一下吗?
That's not going to happen.
那是不可能的
His "thing" isn't tied up, though.
他的“那里”倒是没被绑住
You can still take care of that.
你可以好好照顾那里
That's right!
没错
Arnheid...
阿奴纳
I'm sorry.
对不起
I will
我这辈子
never
再也不会
leave you and Hjalti
把你和贾赫提
alone again.
单独留下了
Never again...
再也不会
I was wrong.
我错了
Please forgive me,
请原谅我
Arnheid.
阿奴纳
I made you suffer so much.
我让你承受了这么多的折磨
Let's start over.
让我们重新开始吧
Let's go back to how it was.
让我们回到从前吧
Please let me free.
请放我自由吧
I'm sorry, Gardar.
对不起 哥达
I'm sorry.
对不起
What are you saying?
你说什么?
I'm the one who must ask for your forgiveness.
要说对不起的人是我才对
Come now, Arnheid.
别这样 阿奴纳
Get a hold of yourself.
你振作一些
That ruined the mood.
还真是扫兴
It's starting to rain harder. I'll take a rest in the hut.
雨势变大了 我去茅屋里休息一下
What? Hey!
什么?
We were told to keep watch.
老大交代我们要一直盯着他
One person is enough.
一个人就绰绰有余
You're the one who brought that woman,
那女人是你带过来的
so you take responsibility.
所以该由你负责
Seriously?
搞什么啊?
Hey.
喂
Hey, Arnheid!
喂 阿奴纳
Are you done? Isn't that enough?
你好了没有啊?够了吧?
My only fault is that I'm a sucker for women.
我唯一的错就是对女人心肠太软
Your time's up.
时间到了
Come on, get up.
快点起来
Arnheid! He has a knife on his belt.
阿奴纳 他的腰带上有一把刀
Use that to cut my rope.
用那把刀来砍断我的绳子
Hurry up! Arnheid!
快点 阿奴纳
Hey! This is bad! He's dead!
喂 情况不妙 他死了
I don't know! Just hurry!
我不知道 快点来就对了
Get it together!
振作一点
Hurry up!
快点
My rope!
我的绳子
We'll both be killed!
我们两个都会没命的
Arnheid!
阿奴纳
It's no use, Boss.
不行了 老大
None of them are breathing.
两人都没有呼吸了
Those idiots.
那群白痴
I told them to not let their guard down so many times.
我说了一百次叫他们不要掉以轻心
Over here, Boss.
老大 在这里
His sword...
他的剑...
Take a look at the tip.
看看剑尖
The rain washed away the blood, but there's still oil on it.
雨水把血迹冲掉了 但上面仍有油渍
He must have stabbed his opponent.
他一定刺伤了他的对手
- That's a deep wound. - Yes.
-伤口一定很深 -没错
He was wounded on top of being wounded already.
他已经有伤在身了 现在更是雪上加霜
There were no horses here either.
这里没有马匹
Go after him!
快去追他
He hasn't gone far.
他还没跑远
We will settle this on this farm!
我会在这座农场把这件事处理干净
As soon as I find him
我一找到他
I will kill him.
就会杀了他
You couldn't sleep,
你睡不着吗?
Einar?
埃纳尔
You haven't slept yourself.
你也还不是一样睡不着
You weren't woken up by a nightmare.
你不是被噩梦惊醒的
Yeah...
对
Were you keeping an eye on me?
你一直留意着我吗?
Did you think I would
你认为我会
do something crazy during the night?
在晚上做出什么傻事吗?
I wouldn't.
我不会的
I don't want to make life harder for Arnheid.
我不会让阿奴纳的心情更不好过
It's not fair, is it?
这很不公平 对吧?
We were just living in peace, that's all.
我们只想安安静静地过日子 仅此而已
Violence
暴力
has robbed us of our freedom, and that's just wrong.
剥夺了我们的自由 这样是不对的
It must be wrong.
肯定是错得离谱
As someone
身为一个
who was doing nothing but fighting wars,
什么都不懂 只知道打打杀杀的人
I don't have the right to say anything.
我没有资格发表意见
But...
但是...
it's wrong.
错了
It was wrong.
确实错了
Arnheid
阿奴纳
doesn't know that you used to be a warrior.
不知道你之前是一名战士
I'm pathetic.
我很可悲
I'm scared
我很害怕
of the thought of people like her finding that out about me.
像她这种人知道了真相之后 对我会产生什么想法
How was I able to hurt all those people
我怎么能够如此若无其事地
like it was nothing?
伤害了这么多人?
I can't even imagine
我完全无法想像
you being that way.
你做得出这种事
Hey Thorfinn,
托尔芬
you know that thing you mentioned before?
你之前跟我提过的那件事...
- Are you serious about it? - What?
-你是认真的吗? -什么事?
Remember you asked me if I thought
你还记得你问过我
it was possible to rid this world
有没有可能让这个世界
of war and slavery?
免于战争和奴役吗?
It just sounds like a dream to me.
对我来说那就像是个梦想
But as someone who has experienced both sides,
但对于有过这两种经历的人来说
I bet you can come up with an idea.
我认为你能想出一个办法
What do we need to do?
我们该怎么做?
How do we
我们该如何
get rid of war and slavery?
摆脱战争和奴役?
I only know
我只知道
about the things I experienced myself.
我亲身经历过的事
But there's no doubt that wars produce many slaves.
但战争造成了很多奴隶 这是不争的事实
Those who are defeated in war
那些在战争中被打败的人
are turned into slaves.
都成了奴隶
Just as you and Arnheid were.
就跟你和阿奴纳一样
The line between warriors and slave traders is ambiguous.
战士和奴隶贩子之间的界限很模糊
There are other things that lead to slavery,
还有其他原因也会制造出奴隶
but I think the biggest cause is war.
但我认为最大的原因是战争
If the number of wars decline the number of slaves will too.
如果战争的数量减少了 奴隶的数量也会随之减少
But Nordic men
但北方人
don't view war as something bad.
不把战争视作一件坏事
Nordic men measure their worth by valor and wealth.
北方人用勇猛和财富 来衡量自己的价值
The more people you kill
他们杀越多的人
and the more wealth you return with, the more you are respected.
因此获得更多的财富 也就能赢得更多人的敬重
That is why fathers teach their sons how to fight,
所以做父亲的会教儿子如何战斗
give them weapons and armor, and take them on warships.
给他们武器和盔甲 带他们上战舰
That has always been the normal thing to do
对于北方人来说 这些行为
for us Nordic men.
都相当合情合理
Whatever it is, it's always difficult to stop doing what is considered the norm.
只要是想打破常规 不管内容是什么 永远都是很困难的
But there are also men like you.
但是 也会有像你这样的人
Is vowing to never hurt another person
发誓再也不伤害任何人
such a strange thing to do?
这样真的很奇怪吗?
In Nordic society,
在北方人的社会里
cowards cannot survive.
懦夫是活不下去的
But that's fine.
但那也没关系
If it means I don't have to carry any more of them,
如果这表示我不需要 再背负他们的罪责
I would happily be an outcast.
我乐于当一个边缘人
"Them"?
“他们”?
The dead.
死人
The people I have killed.
那些被我杀死的人
Their ghosts appear before me almost every night
他们的灵魂 几乎每晚都会出现在我眼前
and torment me.
折磨我
They say, "Why did you kill?
他们说:“你为什么要杀人?
After your father was killed,
在你父亲被杀了之后
you were so angry and resentful.
你是如此愤怒和怨恨
So why did you, out of all people, kill so many
你竟然还能够杀了这么多
fathers, brothers, and sons?"
人父、人子、人兄、人弟?”
I have to make amends
我必须对那些人
for what I did to these people.
做出补偿
I have to take these people to a place
我必须把这些人带到一个
where they can rest in peace.
能够让他们安息的地方
I'm at my limit.
我已经到达极限了
I can't take on even one more person.
我没办法再多背负一个人了
I'm constantly thinking
我一直不停地想着
about how I can repay them.
我该如何补偿他们
Vowing to never kill or destroy anything anymore isn't enough
发誓绝不再杀害任何人、摧毁任何事
to be called atonement.
并不足以被称为赎罪
To make up for all the wheat I've trampled on,
为了弥补那些被我践踏蹂躏过的麦田
I have to grow more with my own hands.
我必须亲手栽种出更多的小麦
To make up for all the houses I've burned down,
为了弥补那些被我烧毁的房子
I have to build more with my own hands.
我得亲手盖出更多的房子
I still don't know how to rid this entire world
我还是不知道该如何让这个世界
of war altogether.
免于战争
But even if it's just one place in this world...
但即使这世上只有一个地方
It could even be just one village...
即使只是一个村庄
I want to create
我想要创造一个
a place where we no longer need swords.
刀剑无用武之地的地方
But
但是
how would you protect that place?
你要如何保护那个地方?
I hate war myself.
我本身也很憎恨战争
But Vikings will come wherever you are.
但不管你去到哪里 维京人一定会找上门
Sometimes you have to fight
有时候为了保护你的和平和自由
to protect your peace and freedom.
你必须挺身而战
But
但是
that won't do.
那没有用
There's no point if you use war to keep peace.
用战争来寻求和平是缘木求鱼
If you do,
如果你这么做
you'll never be able to escape from that bloodstained hell.
你将永远无法逃离血迹斑斑的地狱
I guess
我想
a story that sounds like a dream
一件听起来像是梦想的事
is nothing but a dream.
终究也只是一个梦想
We have to go to the ends of the earth,
我们得去到地球的尽头
somewhere far, far away.
一个很远很远的地方
Somewhere even Vikings can't get to.
就连维京人也到不了的地方
A land
一片只属于
just for outcasts.
边缘人的土地
If we run away far beyond the ocean,
如果我们远渡重洋
I wonder what we'll find there.
不知道会发现什么呢?
I'm sure
我肯定
there will be nothing.
那里一定什么都没有
No matter how far you go, it'll be the same as it is here.
不管你跑得多远 都会跟这里一模一样
There will only be war and slave traders.
只会有战争和奴隶贩子
Far west...
遥远的西方
Beyond the ocean...
远渡重洋
A land out of the reach of any ruler,
一个任何统治者都到不了的地方
a land no slave trader knows about,
一个任何奴隶贩子都不知道的地方
a land far beyond the horizon.
一个在地平线另一端的地方
There is actually a place like that?
这样的一个地方真的存在吗?
There is. I had forgotten about it.
存在 我曾经忘了这件事
When I was a child, a sailor named Leif
当我还小的时候 有个名叫雷夫的水手
told me about it.
跟我说过这个地方
Beyond the vast ocean to the west,
向西航行 远渡重洋之后
there supposedly is fertile land.
会抵达一片肥沃的陆地
He said there's land that's untouched.
他说那里有块处女地
That's amazing.
太神奇了
Then... Then if we go there...
那么...如果我们去到那里
No...
没办法...
He also told me that it is tremendously far.
他也告诉我那里十分的遥远
And I don't know the exact location.
我也不知道确切的地点
Plus, we're talking about building a nation.
况且 我们现在谈论的是 建立一个国度
We have to take a multitude of outcasts there.
我们得带上为数众多的 边缘人跟我们一起去
It'll be a huge project.
这会是一个庞大的计划
I see.
我明白了
But you know,
但你知道吗?
that's the best thing I've heard in a while.
这是我这一阵子以来 听过的最棒的一件事
Be careful.
小心
He's strong.
他很厉害
Wh... What is going on
一大早的
so early in the morning?
发生了什么事吗?
It doesn't seem like anyone's here.
看起来这里应该没人
I can't tell with all this junk.
垃圾这么多 我实在分辨不出来
Throw everything out!
把所有的东西都搬出去
Jeez, what is this all about?
天啊 这究竟是怎么回事?
He escaped.
他逃跑了
- What? - Gardar escaped.
-什么? -哥达逃跑了
Is there any other reason why they would be ransacking our shed?
不然他们还会为了什么原因 这么仔细地搜查我们的小屋?
Arnheid!
阿奴纳
''Cause.''
大义
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻译:朱未耒